Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
They don’t sell this kind
of meth in a back alley.
In today’s story, we
look at the ill effects
of an excess of methionine,
an amino acid that can cause
cancerous tumors to grow
and our lifespan to shrink.
This recent review,
noting that vegan diets,
in part because they tend to be
naturally low in methionine,
may prove to be a useful
nutritional strategy
in cancer
growth control,
also looked at methionine restriction
and life-span extension.
It seems that the less methionine
there is in body tissues,
the longer different
animals tend to live.
But what are the possible
implications for humans?
I've talked before about the
free radical theory of aging,
this concept that aging
can be thought of
as the oxidation
of our bodies
just like rust is the
oxidation of metal,
and methionine is thought to
have a "pro-oxidant effect."
So the thinking is that
lower methionine intake
leads to less free
radical production—
the so-called reactive
oxygen species,
which slows the rate
of DNA damage,
which then would slow the
rate of DNA mutation,
slowing the rate of
aging and disease,
thereby potentially
increasing our lifespan.
There are three ways to
lower methionine intake,
caloric restriction—they call
it dietary restriction here,
meaning like you cut your
intake of food in half,
for example only eating
every other day.
That would lower your
methionine intake...
Or, because methionine is found
concentrated in
certain proteins,
you could practice protein
restriction across the board,
eating a relatively
protein deficient diet.
Or the third option is
to eat enough food,
eat enough protein, but
just eat plant protein,
because they are relatively
low in methionine.
Caloric restriction is hard,
because you walk around
starving all the time.
Something like
every-other-day eating
is never likely to
gain much popularity
as a pro-longevity
strategy for humans,
so it may be
more feasible
to achieve moderate
methionine restriction,
in light of the fact
that plant-based diets
tend to be relatively
low in this amino acid.
As we've seen, plant products
tend to be lower
in methionine than
animal products.
Yes, protein restriction
across the board
can be performed to avoid the
hunger of caloric restriction,
but again, methionine restriction
could also be performed
emphasizing low-methionine,
high quality
vegetable sources
of protein.
Among foods containing
plant proteins,
legumes are especially rich
in essential amino acids,
offering excellent substitutes
for proteins of animal origin.
The fact that beans have
comparatively low methionine
has been classically
considered a disadvantage.
But given the capacity
of methionine restriction
to decrease the rate of
free radical generation
in internal organs,
to lower markers
of chronic disease,
and to increase
maximum longevity
ironically converts such a “disadvantage”
into a strong advantage
and fits well with the
important role of beans
in healthy diets like the
traditional Mediterranean diet.
Interestingly, soy protein is also
especially poor in methionine,
and it is widely considered
that soy-containing foods
have healthy effects
in human beings.
Now, on a population level
folks could benefit from just
lowering their protein intake.
Period!
"The mean intake of proteins
(and thus methionine)
of Western human populations
is much higher than needed.
Therefore, decreasing such
levels has a great potential
to lower tissue
oxidative stress
and to increase healthy
life span in humans
while avoiding the possible undesirable
effects of caloric restriction."
First thing we can
recommend is just decreasing
the intake of protein,
that has a large potential
to bring about
health benefits,
but then we can lower
methionine even further
eating a plant-based diet.
The reason plant-based diets
are so protective
is not known.
Yes, vegetables contain
thousands of phytochemicals,
but separately investigating
their possible protective roles
will be an impossible task.
The idea that the
protective effect
is not due to any of the
individual plant food components,
but to a synergic “combined effect”
is gaining acceptance.
However, based on
the relationship
of excess dietary methionine
with toxicity
to major vital organs and its
likely mechanism of action
through increase in free
radical generation,
the possibility exists that
the protective effects
of plant-based
diets can be due,
at least in part, to their
lower methionine content.
This is not
a new idea.
It was proposed
back in 2009,
but is only now gaining
increasing acceptance
in more mainstream
scientific circles.
The idea that "The low-methionine
content of vegan diets
may make methionine restriction feasible
as a life extension strategy."
In our next story, we learn
how plant-based diets
may prove to be a
useful nutrition strategy
because these diets are
naturally lower in methionine.
In designing an antibiotic,
you wouldn't create a drug
that destroyed DNA, for example,
because that's something that both
humans and bacteria share in common.
It would kill the
bacteria, all right,
but it might kill us too.
So, many antibiotics work by
attacking the bacterial cell wall,
something bacteria
have that we don't.
Antifungals can attack the
unique cell walls of fungus.
Pesticides can work by attacking
the special exoskeleton of insects.
But fighting cancer is harder,
because cancer cells
are our own cells.
So, fighting cancer comes down
to trying to find and exploit
differences between cancer
cells and normal cells.
Forty years ago, a landmark
paper was published
showing for the first time
that many human cancers
have what's called absolute
methionine dependency,
meaning you can grow normal
cells in a petri dish
without given them the
amino acid methionine—
normal cells thrive,
but without methionine,
cancer cells die.
Normal breast cells, for example,
grow no matter what,
with or without,
but here's leukemia cells—
they need that extra
added methionine
to grow or they just flat-line.
What does cancer do
with the methionine?
Tumors generate gaseous sulphur-
containing compounds with it,
that specially trained diagnostic
dogs can actually pick up.
There are mole sniffing dogs
that can pick out skin cancer.
There are breath-sniffing dogs
that can pick out people
with lung cancer.
Pee-sniffing dogs that can
diagnose bladder cancer and,
yes - you guessed it.
Fart-sniffing dogs for
colorectal cancer.
Doctors can now bring
their lab to the lab…
Gives a whole new meaning
to the term "pet scan."
Anyway, methionine dependency
is not just present in cancer
cell lines in a petri dish,
Fresh tumors taken from patients
show that many cancers
appear to have
biochemical defects
that makes them
methionine dependent,
including some tumors
of the colon, breast,
ovary, prostate, and skin.
Chemo companies are
fighting to be the first
to come out with a methionine-
depleting drug,
but since methionine is
sourced mainly from food
a better strategy may be
to lower methionine levels
by lowering methionine intake,
eliminating high methionine foods,
for cancer growth control.
Here's the thinking:
look, smoking cessation,
consumption of diets rich in plants,
and other lifestyle measures
can prevent the
majority of cancers.
Unfortunately, people don't
do them, and as a result,
each year hundreds of thousands of
Americans develop metastatic cancer.
Chemotherapy cures only a few
types of metastatic cancer.
Unfortunately, the vast majority
of common metastatic cancers,
like breast, prostate, colon,
and lung are lethal.
We therefore desperately need novel treatment
strategies for metastatic cancer,
and dietary methionine restriction
may be one such strategy.
So, where is methionine found?
Particularly, chicken and fish,
milk, red meat and eggs have less,
but if you really want to stick
with lower methionine foods,
fruits, nuts, veggies,
grains, and beans.
In other words, methionine
restriction may be achieved
using a predominantly vegan diet.
So, why isn't every
oncologist doing this?
"Despite many promising preclinical and
clinical studies in recent years,
dietary methionine restriction
and other dietary approaches
to cancer treatment have not yet gained
widespread clinical application.
Most clinicians and investigators
are probably unfamiliar
with nutritional approaches to cancer"...
(ah...that's an understatement).
"Many others may consider amino acid
restriction as an 'old idea',
since it has been examined
for several decades.
However, many good ideas remain
latent for decades if not centuries
before they prove
valuable in the clinic.
With the proper development,
dietary methionine restriction,
either alone or in combination
with other treatments,
may prove to have a major impact
on patients with cancer.“
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social media
to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition
Facts Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on
the pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book, audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book, “How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out my second-to-last
book,  my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.  It’s
beautifully designed with more than 100
recipes  for delicious and nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds I receive from
the sales  of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.